Guide to the William L. Smith papers 1946-2008 MS2258
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
William L. Smith papers
1946-2008
1970-1985
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Smith, William Lee
MS2258
6.25 Linear Feet
This collection contains speeches, articles, professional journals, books, photographs, scrap books, reports, and other material. The material dates from 1946-2008, but the material predominately dates from 1970-1985. These are the speeches, published writings, resources, and other material of William L. Smith. William "Bill" Smith was an education leader, teacher, reformer, and author who held many top-echelon posts at the U.S. Department of Education and its predecessor the U.S. Office of Education for 37 years. Smith published many articles in a wide variety of journals and books. The material reflects a variety of topics, including multiculturalism in education, teacher education, federal education policies, and education reform.
Scope and Content note
This collection contains speeches, published articles, unpublished manuscripts, professional journals, books, photographs, scrap books, brochures, reports, clippings, event programs, VHS tapes, and a yearbook. The material dates from 1946-2008, but the material predominately dates from 1970-1985. These are the speeches, published writings, resources, and other material of William L. Smith from his time working at the U.S. Office of Education and U.S. Department of Education. Smith served as director of Teacher Corps, U.S. Commissioner of Education, and in many other senior posts. The material reflects a variety of topics, including multiculturalism in education, teacher education, federal education policies, and education reform. The collection was donated by Smith's widow in 2009.
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for research.
Arrangement note
Organized into three series: Writings of William Smith, Commemorative material, and Educational resources.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift of Audrey Smith, 12/22/2008, (2008.058)
Biographical/Historical note
William L. "Bill" Smith (1929-2008) was an education leader, teacher, reformer, and author who held many top-echelon posts at the U.S. Department of Education and its predecessor the U.S. Office of Education for 37 years.
Smith was born on January 3, 1929 in Boston, Massachusetts. He attended Jefferson School in Jamaica Plains, the Asa Grade School, the C.C. Perkins School, Julia Ward Howe Elementary School, the Tyler School, and the Abraham Lincoln School. Smith Sr. enrolled his son in the Boston Technical High School after William's mother died and William moved into the Charles Hayden Goodwill Inn for Boys in the South End of Boston. William attended Claflin College (Orangeburg, SC) and then Wiley College (Marshal, TX) where he received a presidential and music scholarship. He played in the marching band and joined the Omega Psi Phi fraternity. He graduated with a Bachelor of Arts in 1949. He returned to Boston and was awarded a fellowship at Boston University. In 1950, he enrolled in the U.S. Army and was sent to Korea. He was among the first African Americans to serve in and thus integrate the army's First Cavalry Division. Smith earned a Bronze Star and a Purple Heart in Korea. He was assigned to the 3rd Battalion Intelligence Section and he was eventually promoted to the rank of master sergeant and taught military intelligence. He was honorably discharged in 1953. Smith earned a Master's degree from the Massachusetts State Teachers College (now UMass Boston) in 1955. He married Mable Lucille Madison of Colfax, Iowa and they moved to Cleveland, Ohio. He joined the Cleveland Pubic Schools as a history teacher at the East Technical High School. Smith became an outdoor track coach and a guidance counselor. In 1965 Smith was hired as principal of Patrick Henry Junior High School, which was a struggling inner city school. He began to make changes and even kept the school open until 9:30 pm. Patrick Henry became the best junior high school in Cleveland. His success there propelled him into a national spotlight and he served on the President's National Advisory Council on Title III of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act. Smith began work on a Ph.D. at Case Western Reserve University in 1958, but he did not finish it until 1970. He left Patrick Henry and served as executive director of the Program for Action by Citizens in Education (PACE).
Smith moved to the Washington, DC area in 1969 and began work at the Office of Education. He worked under Associate Commissioner Don Davies in the Bureau of Education and Personnel Development. From 1971 to 1979, Smith directed Teacher Corps. He was named U.S. Commissioner of Education of the U.S. Office of Education in 1979. He was the only civil service employee to come up through the ranks to become commissioner, he was the first and only African American education commissioner, and he was the very last education commissioner. The Office of Education became the Department of Education in 1980 and Smith continued to hold prominent positions until his retirement in 2006.
In 1999 Smith was inducted into the National Alliance of Black School Educator's Hall of Fame. He received six honorary degrees and several presidential recognitions, including Senior Executive Service Charter Member (1979) and Presidential Rank Award (1981, 1990, and 1994). Smith published many articles in a wide variety of journals and books. Smith was interviewed by the HistoryMakers on September 9, 2003.
Bill Smith passed away on February 29, 2008 at Holy Cross Hospital, Silver Springs, MD. He was survived by wife Audrey, their children, Warren Smith; Denise Smith Withers; Kraig Boone; Kay Boone, and five grandchildren. Sources: Beverly E. Coleman, "William L. (Bill) Smith, 'Mr. Commissioner'" 1982 Afro-American History Kit, The Association for the Study of Afro-American Life and History, Inc., 1982; "Bill Smith: A Leader and a Legend," Insider ED, Vol. XIX, No. 6, June/July 2006; and William L. Smith, "Professional Development and School Administration: A Collection of Articles," 2000.
Education
- Writings of William Smith, 1966-2000; 1970-1985; Series 1; 3.5 Linear Feet
  Scope and Content note
  This series contains speeches, published articles, unpublished manuscripts, professional journals, books, brochures, reports, and event programs. The material dates from 1966-2000, but the material predominately dates from 1970-1985. These are the speeches and published writings of William L. Smith from his time working at the U.S. Office of Education and U.S. Department of Education. Smith served as director of Teacher Corps, U.S. Commissioner of Education, and in many other senior posts. The material reflects a variety of topics, including multiculturalism in education, teacher education, federal education policies, and education reform.
  Arrangement note
  This series is organized alphabetically by publication title.
  - Speeches by Dr. Smith Index, 07/18/1974-03/28/1985; MSS2258 Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Speeches [1 of 6], 07/18/1974-02/20/1979; MSS2258 Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Speeches [2 of 6], 02/28/1979-02/18/1980; MSS2258 Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Speeches [3 of 6], 02/23/1980-03/29/1980; MSS2258 Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Speeches [4 of 6], 04/12/1980-07/17/1980; MSS2258 Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Speeches [5 of 6], 07/28/1980-04/08/1981 and undated; MSS2258 Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Speeches [6 of 6], 04/27/1983-12/08/1987 and undated; MS2258 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - American Education, 11/1971-02/1980; MSS2258 Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - A Design for a School of Pedagogy, 1980; MSS2258 Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Educating for Diversity / Family Strengths 7, 1986-1995; MSS2258 Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Inservice Education: Demonstrating Local Programs, 1978; MSS2258 Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Issues in Inservice Education, 1976; MSS2258 Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Journal of Teacher Education, 1974; MSS2258 Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Journal of Teacher Education, 1975; MSS2258 Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Multicultural Education Through Competency-based Teacher Education, 1974; MSS2258 Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Multiculturalism and Diversity: A Collection of Articles, 2000; MSS2258 Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Perspectives on Organization, 1976-1977; MSS2258 Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Phi Delta Kappan, 01/1972; MSS2258 Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Politics of Competence: A Review of Competency-based Teacher Education, 1975; MSS2258 Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Principal, 04/1972; MSS2258 Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Pro Excellentia, 04/1968; MSS2258 Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Professional Development and School Administration: A Collection of Articles, 2000; MSS2258 Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Professional Development and School Administration: A Collection of Articles, 2000; MSS2258 Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Professional Development of Teachers, 1980; MSS2258 Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - The Range of Variability: Inservice Design in Special Education, 1977; MSS2258 Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Schooling and Society, 1981; MSS2258 Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Teaching Corps, undated; MSS2258 Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Teaching Corps Alumni Network Symposia Proceedings, 1988-1989; MSS2258 Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Teaching Corps 74: 8th and 9th Cycle Conference, 06/09/1974-06/13; MSS2258 Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Teaching Corps National Conference Report 1977, MSS2258 Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Teaching Corps Conference 1974: A Sharing of Experiences, MSS2258 Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Teaching Corps National Conference Report 1978, MSS2258 Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Ten Years of Teaching Corps 1966-1976, MSS2258 Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Todays Education, 10/1969; MSS2258 Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Together: 10th Cycle Corps Member Training Institute, 1975; MSS2258 Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Multiculturalism binder [1 of 2], circa 1999; MSS2258 Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Multiculturalism binder [2 of 2], circa 1999; MSS2258 Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - The Task Ahead, circa 1975; MSS2258 Series 1 (Flat box 10, Item 1)
  - The Task Ahead, circa 1975; MSS2258 Series 1 (Flat box 10, Item 2)
  - Teacher Corps 8th and 9th Cycle Conference: Accepting the Range of Human Variability, 06/09/1974-06/13/1974; MSS2258 Series 1 (Flat box 10, Item 3)
  - Teacher Corps 8th and 9th Cycle Conference: Accepting the Range of Human Variability, 06/09/1974-06/13/1974; MSS2258 Series 1 (Flat box 10, Item 4)
- Commemorative material, 1946-2008; 1970-2006; Series 2; 1.5 Linear Feet
  This series contains photographs, notes, a year book, award ceremony programs, biographical information, scrap books, and some clippings. The material dates from 1946-2008, but the material predominately dates from 1970-2006. These are material that commemorate and celebrate the life and work of William L. Smith. They range from in date from his high school years to his 2006 retirement from the U.S. Department of Education.
  This series is organized by material type and is neither alphabetical nor chronological.
  - Photographs, undated; MSS2258 Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Photographs, undated; MSS2258 Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Photograph, Senator Kennedy and William Smith, 07/26/1975; MSS2258 Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - The Technician: Boston Technical High School yearbook, 1946; MSS2258 Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Clipping, 1977-1980; MSS2258 Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Eastern Michigan University Commencement program, 04/19/1980; MSS2258 Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Fordham University Scanlon Award program, 04/25/1977; MSS2258 Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Biographical information, 1982-2006; MSS2258 Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Memorial Tribute: Dr. William L. "Bill" Smith program, 03/19/2008; MSS2258 Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Teachers Corps Memories, Dr. William L. Smith, October 1, 1973 - January 8, 1980, MSS2258 Series 2 (Flat box 11, Item 1)
  - Department of Education retirement album, 2006; MSS2258 Series 2 (Flat box 11, Item 2)
- Education resources, 1970-1989; 1970-1985; Series 3; 1.25 Linear Feet
  This series contains books, published articles, professional journals, brochures, reports, and VHS videos. The material dates from 1970-1989, but it predominately dates from 1970-1985. These are materials relate to William L. Smith's work at the U.S. Office of Education and U.S. Department of Education. Smith served as director of Teacher Corps, U.S. Commissioner of Education, and in many other senior posts. The material reflects a variety of topics, including multiculturalism in education, teacher education, federal education policies, and education reform.
  This series is organized alphabetically by publication title. VHS tapes are at the end of the series.
  - Comparative Theories of Social Change, 1966; MSS2258 Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - The Education Professions 1971-1972: Part III, 1973; MSS2258 Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - The Five Dimensions of Demonstration: Teacher Corp Research Cluster, 1977; MSS2258 Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Growing Pains in the Classroom: A Guide for Teachers of Adolescents, 1977; MSS2258 Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Impact of the Teacher Corps Program on Teaching Education and Certification Requirements: A Case Study, 1984; MSS2258 Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - In Praise of Diversity: Multicultural Classroom Applications, 1977; MSS2258 Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Lessons from the Teacher Corps, 1974; MSS2258 Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Management and Machiavelli: An Inquiry into the Politics of Corporate Life, undated; MSS2258 Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - A Nation at Risk: The Imperative for Education Reform, 1983; MSS2258 Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Networks: A Review of the Teacher Corps Theory and Practice of Networks for Supporting Local Projects, 1978; MSS2258 Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Teacher Corps Cycle XII Program, 1978; MSS2258 Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Teacher Corps 11th and 12th Cycle Training Conference, 08/03/1977-08/03/1977; MSS2258 Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Teacher Corps Portraits: Four Case Studies, 12/1977; MSS2258 Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Teacher Corps Program Directory 1976-1977, 10/31/1976; MSS2258 Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Teacher Corps Program Directory 1978-1979, 01/12/1979; MSS2258 Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Teachers for the Changing World: A Multinational View, 06/1976; MSS2258 Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Who Runs Our Schools?: The Changing Face of Educational Leadership, 1989; MSS2258 Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - List of removed books, undated; MSS2258 Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - VHS video, Roundtable VI - McClure, Winston, and Gerry presentation, undated; MSS2258 Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - VHS video, USC NAI PCEA possible shelves, undated; MSS2258 Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 2)